Finding Aid for the Coleman A. Harwell Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Coleman A. Harwell Papers
multiple
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0797
0.21 linear_feet
Biographical Note:
Coleman Alexander Harwell was born in 1905 in Nashville, Tennessee and graduated from the University of the South at Sewanee, TN in 1926. He began his career as a journalist when he joined the Nashville Tennessean as a reporter in 1927. He served as editor of The Tennessean from 1948 until 1959, and later published newspapers in Cookeville and Sparta, Tennessee. While at The Tennessean he hired and helped advance the careers of some of the most respected journalists in America including David Halberstam, Tom Wicker, and John Seigenthaler. Coleman A. Harwell died on February 26, 1987 at the age of 81. As part of his will, Harwell established the Mary McClure Hotchkiss Scholarship at Vanderbilt University in memory of his aunt.
Scope and Content Note:
The Coleman Harwell Papers consist of six folders. Researchers will find photographs of Coleman Harwell; correspondence between him and his peers from 1953 – 1958; notes Harwell collected; and a 1954 article concerning an attack on a reporter of The Nashville Tennessean.
- Photographs (Folder 1)
  - Coleman Harwell and unidentified man in The Tennessean newsroom ca. mid 1950’s
- Correspondence – 1953 (Folder 2)
  - Letter to V.M. Newton, Jr., February 25, 1953
  - Letter to Ellis Binkley, James S. Pope, February 25, 1953
  - Lettter to CAH from V. M. Newton, Jr., February 27, 1953
  - Letter to CAH from James S. Pope, March 3, 1953
  - Photocopy of letter to CAH, March 3, 1953
  - Letter to CAH from James S. Pope, March 3, 1953
  - Letter to V.M. Newton, Jr., March 5, 1953
  - Letter to Walker Stone, March 5, 1953
  - Letter to CAH from V.M. Newton, Jr. “Interim Report Of the Committee for Advancement of Freedom of Information of Sigma Delta Chi Fraternity”, April 30, 1953
  - Photocopy of letter to CAH from V.M. Newton, Jr., April 30, 1953
  - Letter to “Red” V. M. Newton, Jr., May 15, 1953
  - Letter to CAH from V.M. Newton, Jr., May 19, 1953
  - Photocopy of letter to CAH from V.M. Newton, Jr., May 19, 1953
- Correspondence – 1954 (Folder 3)
  - Letter to CAH from V. M. Newton, Jr., March 10, 1954
  - Letter to CAH from Lois Laycook, March 10, 1954
  - Photocopy of letter to CAH from Lois Laycook, March10, 1954
  - Letter to “Red” V. M. Newton, Jr., April 12, 1954
  - Photocopy of letter to “Red” V.M. Newton, Jr., April 12, 1954
  - Article for the ASNE Bulletin by CAH, August 1954
  - Photocopy of article for ASNE Bulletin by CAH, August 1954
- Correspondence – 1955 -1958 (Folder 4)
  - Letter from Charlie Fontenay to CAH “Secrecy in Government”, July 15, 1955
  - Letter to The Tennessean Staff, July 19, 1955
  - Letter to Representative W.C. Herrell from V. M. Newton, Jr., February 5, 1958
  - Letter to CAH from Herbert Brucker, November 7, 1958
  - Letter to V.M. Newton, Jr., November 27, 1958
  - Letter to Carl A. Jones, November 27, 1958
  - Letter to Loye W. Miller, November 27, 1958
  - Letter to Dave Schutz, November 27, 1958
  - Letter to Mason Walsh, November 27, 1958
  - Letter to CAH from V. M. Newton, Jr., December 2, 1958
  - Letter to Clement Brossier, December 2, 1958
  - Letter to Morrie Landsberg, December 2, 1958
  - Letter to Fred Siebert, December 2, 1958
  - Letter to Herbert Brucker, December 3, 1958
  - Letter to James “Jimmie” S. Pope, December 3, 1958
  - Letter to Russ Wiggins, December 3, 1958
  - Telefax to Paul Fisher from CAH, December 3, 1958
  - Letter to CAH from Elmer White, December 3, 1958
  - Telefax to Wallace Lomoe from CAH, December 4, 1958
  - Letter to David Schutz from Robert G. Fichenberg, December 5, 1958
  - Letter to David Schutz from CAH, December 30, 1958
- Notes (Folder 5)
  - “Agenda Freedom of Information Center Advisory Committee”
  - “Courtroom Photography – A Case Proven” speech by Creed C. Black before the Tennessee Bar Association, Columbia, Tennessee, January 24, 1958
  - Harwell notes on legal paper
- News Articles (Folder 6)
  - Pulaski. “Steadman Attorneys Attack Newsman” in The Nashville Tennessean (2), August 19, 1954